<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://jz-jun.github.io//feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://jz-jun.github.io//" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-10-22T17:16:48+00:00</updated><id>https://jz-jun.github.io//feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Being Detail-Oriented</title><link href="https://jz-jun.github.io//blog/2025/details/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Being Detail-Oriented"/><published>2025-09-19T21:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-09-19T21:01:00+00:00</updated><id>https://jz-jun.github.io//blog/2025/details</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jz-jun.github.io//blog/2025/details/"><![CDATA[<p>…..coming soon….</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="research"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[What I learned about being detail-oriented]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What is research?</title><link href="https://jz-jun.github.io//blog/2025/one/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What is research?"/><published>2025-07-05T15:12:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-07-05T15:12:00+00:00</updated><id>https://jz-jun.github.io//blog/2025/one</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jz-jun.github.io//blog/2025/one/"><![CDATA[<p>I started writing these reflections at the beginning of my PhD to capture lessons I might otherwise forget. I have never been good at taking notes (I once believed I had a good memory and didn’t need notes…turns out, not really..), so I want to document these moments here as memories of my research journey. Here is a short reflection on the first lesson I learned from my master’s advisor and how it shaped the way I think about research.</p> <h3 id="what-i-learned-about-research"><strong>What I Learned About Research</strong></h3> <p>I began my research journey the summer before starting my master’s at UC Irvine. Back then, I wasn’t sure what my role was in a project, and I had no idea what “doing research” meant in the broader context of the HCI community. The very first lessons my advisor shared with me gave me a broad picture of what research is and what it takes to do it.</p> <p><strong>So, What is Research?</strong><br/> At its core, research is about asking the right questions: What are you doing? Why are you doing this? How are you doing this? From there, it becomes a process of shaping the project, selecting appropriate methods, carrying out the work of analysis, and finally, communicating the results. Research is not about rushing to answers; it is about building a thoughtful process that connects questions, methods, and contributions.</p> <p>Key takeaways:</p> <ul> <li>Start with the questions: What are you doing? Why are you doing this? How are you doing this?</li> <li>Formulating the project.</li> <li>Formulating the methods/ Choosing and applying methods (executing the work and analyzing data).</li> <li>Writing up the findings/data.</li> </ul> <p>These takeaways shaped how I began to approach projects, but applying them in practice was not always straightforward. In fact, many of the lessons I learned came from struggling with the day-to-day realities of research.</p> <p><strong>Lessons from Doing Research</strong><br/> I was frustrated when I worked on my first project for many reasons. One of them was that the project timeline felt so long, and I kept going back and forth doing data analysis over and over again. At one point, I honestly just wanted to give up. That was when my advisor reminded me that academic research is all about patience. I began to realize another lesson my advisor often emphasized: progress takes time, and results are not always immediate. What matters is staying committed and steady.</p> <p>In addition, I was not a detail-oriented person before, and I also did not fully understand the purpose of planning and goal-setting. I remember that during the first few meetings with my advisor, I sent her a document with just a few sentences summarizing the project. Looking back, I can see how confusing that must have been. I’ve since learned that being detail-oriented in research isn’t just for yourself. It’s about making your ideas clear enough that others can follow and understand your thinking.</p> <p>Key takeaways:</p> <ul> <li>Research requires initiative. It is really about getting the work done.</li> <li>Working on research is a serious commitment. It asks for persistence and responsibility over the long term.</li> <li>Being detail-oriented is critical. Small things matter, and overlooking them can change the outcome.</li> <li>Making progress toward a Ph.D. means setting clear goals and staying mindful of them.</li> <li>Building routines, habits, and priorities that you will not compromise on makes it easier to stay on track.</li> </ul> <p>These lessons are just the beginning. They shaped how I approached my first projects and continue to guide the way I think about research and grow as a scholar.</p> <p>*© 2025 Jun Zhu. All rights reserved.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="research"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A note on the first lesson my advisor taught me.]]></summary></entry></feed>